Do you like to start your day with a cup of joe?
你喜欢以一杯咖啡开启新的一天吗？
Well, you wouldn’t be alone.
嗯，你不是一个人。
Millions of people from all over the world brew a cup of coffee first thing in the morning, or at any time of day, for that matter.
世界各地数以百万计的人早上的第一件事就是冲泡（brew）一杯咖啡，或者在一天中的任何时候来上一杯。
Do you make it yourself, using instant coffee?
你是自己冲泡速溶咖啡吗？
Or, if you are a coffee connoisseur, perhaps you use freshly ground beans.
或者，如果你是一位咖啡行家（connoisseur），也许你会用现磨的咖啡豆。
Do you take it straight?
你会直接喝纯咖啡吗？
With a dash of milk?
还是加少许牛奶？
Or maybe even some chocolate sprinkles?
或者甚至撒上一些巧克力屑（sprinkles）呢？
Or, failing all of that, maybe you’d rather pay a barista in a cafe to whip one up for you.
或者，如果这些都不喜欢，也许你更愿意付钱给咖啡馆的咖啡师（barista），让他为你快速制作一杯。
Cafes are everywhere these days, offering as many varieties of coffee as there are ways to have it served.
如今咖啡馆无处不在，提供的咖啡种类与供应方式同样多种多样。
And this leads to a range of prices, from cheap grab-and-go coffee, to the ultra-expensive artisanal coffee.
这就导致了咖啡价格的差异，从便宜的即买即走的咖啡，到极其昂贵的手工制作的（artisanal）咖啡。
However, an increasing number of Western consumers are happy to pay a little over the odds for their cup in order to ensure that it comes from an ethically produced and sustainable source.
然而，越来越多的西方消费者乐于为他们的咖啡多（超过正常数量或价格）付一点钱，以便确保咖啡来自符合道德规范且可持续生产的源头。
At The Attendant, a cafe in east London, staff attempt to make customers aware of the story of the beans that they are drinking and the impact they are having by choosing to drink ethically.
在伦敦东部的一家名为“服务员”（The Attendant）的咖啡馆里，员工们试图让顾客了解他们所喝的咖啡豆的故事，以及他们选择符合道德规范的咖啡所产生的影响。
For a start, it can make coffee farmers up to three-and-a-half times better off, according to figures from the UN’s World Intellectual Property Organisation (Wipo).
首先，根据联合国世界知识产权组织（Wipo）的数据，这可以使咖啡农的收入提高多达三倍半。
Ryan de Oliveria, The Attendant's co-founder and chief executive, says the extra income allows farmers and their families to have a better quality of life.
“服务员”咖啡馆的联合创始人兼首席执行官瑞安・德奥利维拉（Ryan de Oliveria）表示，额外的收入使农民及其家人能够过上更好的生活质量。
It also makes investing or reinvesting in their business possible.
这也使他们在自己的生意上进行投资或再投资成为可能。
Wipo’s figures show smarter processing, branding and marketing make a huge difference to the growers and their communities.
世界知识产权组织（Wipo）的数据显示，更智能的加工、品牌打造和市场营销对种植者及其所在社区产生了巨大的影响。
Technology now means that the beans can be tracked all the way from the farm to the cup.
如今的技术意味着咖啡豆从农场到杯子的整个过程都可以被追踪。
The research shows that for a pound (454g) of beans going to a supermarket, the export price is $1.45.
研究表明，一磅（454克）运往超市的咖啡豆，出口价格是1.45美元。
Most of this goes to the farmer.
其中大部分收入归农民所有。
The price almost doubles when the beans are headed for large western coffee chains.
当这些咖啡豆运往西方大型咖啡连锁店时，价格几乎翻倍。
But farmers exporting their beans to artisanal cafes make over $5 per pound.
但是，将咖啡豆出口到手工咖啡馆的农民每磅能赚5美元以上。
That's because the coffee aficionados who frequent these places are happy to pay more.
这是因为经常光顾这些地方的咖啡爱好者（aficionados）乐于支付更高的价格。
It seems that it’s a win-win situation for the farmers, cafes and consumers.
看来这对农民、咖啡馆和消费者来说是一个双赢的局面。
So much so that more established coffee businesses are jumping on the band wagon by buying up artisanal rivals who have already embraced this way of doing things.
以至于更多知名的咖啡企业也开始跟风随大流，收购那些已经采用这种经营方式的手工咖啡竞争对手。
If that’s the case, then the future of coffee production looks a little fairer for all.
如果是这样的话，那么咖啡生产的未来对所有人来说似乎都更公平了一些。
And that’s something that should get anyone up on the right side of bed.
而这是一件能让任何人心情愉悦的事情。